Hello, and welcome to
CS6300 office hour.
Sorry, we are a
little bit late,
but here we are
with Will and Paula.
Hi, everyone.
Hello, everyone.
Okay, so let me look at
the schedule for this
week. So this week,
students are working on
IPD4. this is the last
deliverable and after this
deliverable there will
be no more assignment
though later paula will
post the two readings
the cathedral and the
bazaar and no silver
bullet both are classic
grid and there will be
eight posts for discussing
those two reading
Other than that, we can
go to the questions.
So, first question.
For IPD4, are we allowed
to use our code that
we had written for
IPD3? Yes, of course.
If it's to your own
code, yes, it's allowed.
And in fact, this is
about refactoring and
with refactor, then
supposedly, if you write
the code well, you can
reuse almost all of it.
And that's it for
questions so far.
Do
we have to refactor it to be,
don't repeat yourself, D-R-I?
Well, supposedly,
you should refactor it so
that it can be, so it can
satisfy the requirement
of A4, which is, I think,
this interface. interface.
If you want to
practice the DIY,
yes, you can do so.
But if you don't, then
the gray scope will
not penalize you either.
We don't have specific,
let's say, static
analysis code to see how
many code duplication
this student has and
deduct students for
that. No, we don't have.
It's good practice, but
we don't enforce it.
Very quiet office hours.
We are also very quiet, if I'm
quite waiting for the question.
Yeah,
that's kind of
another question.
There's another one. Yeah,
I saw a post where TA
specified that we do
not need to write
additional test cases.
Could it be good idea
to write test case
for testing? I'm
thinking it could help
write additional test
cases. Thank you. So,
it is true that the
requirement does not require
students to, and there is
no great scope auto grading
enforcement, but of
course, well, on one hand,
if you were doing perfect
IP D1 and D2, then there's
no need for additional
test case for D3 and D4.
It's only that if you were
missing some cases or,
yeah, some edge cases, then
you would need to write
extra. And keep in mind that
sometimes more test cases
does not mean more coverage.
It may just mean duplicates
or meaningless tests. So
that is something that
students and engineers
should pay attention as well.
Yeah, I think it
kind of depends on
when you are writing
your tests in D1.
If you recognize that the
tests that you generated
weren't really complete,
then, you know, it might
make sense to add some
more, but you don't need
to, right? that's
essentially what we're saying
we've only got a
relatively small number of
people here this week
so I mean is it spring
break somewhere else I
don't know but there's
only six students
here at the moment so
they only outnumber
us two to one
there's another one
our own deliverables
for individual
project weighted the same.
Does it have to
do better in the
later deliverable auto crates?
It is weighted more or
less the same. I cannot
confirm nor deny. It
is exactly the same.
Does it have to
do better in the
later deliverable auto crates?
No,
yes and no. I mean,
again, it's more or less
the same, but not
necessarily exactly the same.
So what I would say is
it won't necessarily help
more than the earlier
ones would have. But if
you're not sure you did
well on the earlier ones,
it's certainly going to be
better for you to do well
on the later ones than
not, regardless of what
the rubric is. I don't
know what it currently is.
When I was in charge,
it was roughly equal,
but it would sort of
depend on a few different
things each time as to
things would get shifted
a little bit depending
on where we felt
like there was more
effort involved, we'd give
more points, but it was
generally pretty even.
And I assume there haven't been
radical changes since
then. refreshing
yeah that's that's
what this seltzer
is for is because
it's refreshing
okay if there is
nothing then I don't
know Paula you have
anything new so yes
yes so next week I
think I'm going to LA
maybe in 10 days for
giving a talk at a workshop
collocated with
NASA for my method
conference on
requirements and AI.
And so I extended the
work I was talking
about at the beginning
of the semester.
So funny story is that I'm
working with a high school
student that contacted me
last year saying during the
summer, he contacted me and
said, really, I would really
like, from South Carolina,
it's not even in Georgia.
So he contacted me and I
said, you know, I'm very
interested. This professor
that I know gave me your name.
And so I said, okay, but
you know, I don't really do
a lot of work using AI.
So, but this is what I've
been doing, right? And so
I sent in my work on using
generative AI to make formal
methods more usable and
formal requirements more
usable. And I thought, you
know, as a high school
student, he's going to read
half of the paper and just
say, okay, bye, I'm going to
find something much more
exciting and instead since
then he has learned formal
languages it's like so
now we extended the work on
this and I mean of course
then he likes to do tools
right on and so now we are
working a lot on how you
can interact with the tool
instead of you know we we
did this work in which we
use LLMs to generate explanation
on formal requirements
right but anyway like
they're not always the
explanation are not always
correct like they do pretty
well but they're not always
correct in any way the
explanation it's not a
translation or it's just it's
really to support your
understanding and so now it
created this tool in which
you have different use cases
and different modalities
to use it and you're
trying to analyze and
in the meantime I have a
question in to try to
analyze how to keep the
engagement active of
people so that you don't
lose your ability to
understand and you remain
engaged so you don't
just blindly accept your
so the tool is almost
ready and we are setting a
pilot study to get feedback
this is where we're I
think the student is
undergraduate and he's super on
top of things all the time,
so I'm very impressed.
Wow, that's impressive.
So there is another question?
Okay, what kind of
participation is accepted
on the forum for
reading of the last
week's reading to count
towards the grade?
So the participation
is not only for the
reading, it's throughout
the entire semester.
So being active here,
posting questions on
posting and reading here
is already sufficient.
And when we release the
participation grade,
it will, there will
be breakdown as well.
So don't worry about that.
What's your favorite
formal validation
tools? cork i twist
to snap proof um this
properly um paula
your your expertise
i knew that it's classic
okay so uh honestly i have
been working most of the time
on uh form formal verification
of model using uh uh formal
models right like not
uh not not on code not on so
i am uh automatic theoretical
automatic model checking
like the one that was
invented by clark and emerson
they i think they got a
turing award for it and um
and so i i've used a new smv
spin a lot so spin was was
invented at bell labs and
it's funny because i remember
my first paper as a phd
student was on try to use
so spin used you model your
system as a bouquet automata
that is basically a final
state machine that can
recognize infinite behavior and
and use ltl to specify
properties right and and i
always instead been very
interested in describing your
the system in a descriptive
way so starting and instead
of a you know like an
operational model of the system
is already a step forward
towards where you want to go
and when you study in
requirements you you have
properties right so you have a
more descriptive specification
and they were not tool in
that sense so we i i my
first work was like try to
see if you could you know
simulate a behavior using
existing tool and i was using
spin and i remember my first
paper was the formal method
conference and the invited
speaker and it was like
i don't remember the title
but like a model checking
format descriptive
specification using spin okay
and then the invited speaker
at the conference was
gerald altman that was the
person who invented spin so
i was a phd student that
the first year presenting
the paper using a tool and
in the audience there was
the person that invented
the tool i just like i had
an heart attack in the i
didn't really realize it
so i spoke for 50 minutes
and apparently i was doing
so well and then i saw him
and i choked in the middle
of the presentation uh
but anyway so spin was at
some point died i mean died
it's the same but never
really evolved i think
there is still a community
around it. I think they have
a conference every year.
I actually work a little
bit with which and then
when we died I used a
little bit of new SMB
and I work a little bit
with Alloy. I don't know
if anybody is familiar
that came out from MIT.
It's kind of a lightweight
approach and then from
Alloy there has been a spin
-off that used the core of
Alloy to be able to plug in
different languages and then
I sold my soul to requirements
and so I do much less
formal verification, and
just formal requirements.
Some of the
specification side of it.
Do you guys have
a favorite one?
My would be a Lean
4, just because it
is both implementation
and proof in the
same language. It
feels really, yeah,
like integrated.
And also it has the
kind of compile time.
Well,
the duration of the
compile is fast enough and
it is compile and not
just in time like Java.
So, yeah, it's just, that's
my favorite. it, even
though the more I look
into it, it is said that it
is not as powerful as some
other. There is a different
level of expressiveness
in formal verification.
And I see there is a
question about some
reading, and I'm going
to respond in the chat
about that putting the
link after this office
hour because that
now the literature on
on the on this topic is uh is
exploding exploding um yeah
i'll take care of this
putting also links i
haven't been but last week
there was ICSI that is
probably the main conference
in software engineering and
i was looking at the program
and like finding a paper
without ai in the title was
very difficult yeah it's
one of the reasons i'm kind
of glad i'm i'm retired now
is that you know dealing
with all this ai stuff i'm
really glad i'm not still
in the world of development
while this is going on, I
think it's a difficult time
to be a developer.
But, you know, I don't
know. I think it's kind
of, it's a shaking
moment, right? Like some
of my colleagues work
on trying to analyze,
you know, there are things
that you will analyze
on the long term of the
impact of this revolution,
like what what what
did it mean for a code
maintainability for it's
uh we don't know anything
of this right no i
agree but this is this
is my my old guy you kids
get off my lawn moment
there's another question okay
now i'm not going
to take anymore
how do you think about
problems that have
virtually unlimited
degrees of freedom
and we're using
combinatorics to
determine test frame
is not practical.
The problem has unlimited
degree of freedom.
Anything really have
unlimited degrees of freedom?
i mean and because like
with engineering we always
talk about uh bound right
lower bound upper bound
um and in the in the
model itself is also
have um certain bound
and say even with um
that that's that's the
model right and then
in the implementation
we have uh concrete
let's say float 64
something so technically
we can always brute
force the whole thing.
I don't know, Paola,
what do you think?
I mean then from a
theoretical perspective you
can think of this like
you can go and try to
create a group group
i mean group is wrong
where like uh trying to
understand how you can
what you you know i don't
know like uh i cannot find
the word you can decompose
the problem and trying
to find categories to like
to create a bound because
at the end of the day it's
uh it's So the complexity
of things like autonomous
vehicle, right, is
that anyway, it's what we
produce is finite and you
work with a world that is
potentially, you know, you
cannot predict all the
possible behavior. And so,
very often when you
think about this,
you can verify certain
things and simulate
some others and use
statistical models for
other pieces, but this
is where you're going.
It's not a
combinatory approach.
um yeah i mean the the
combinatorial approach can
itself uh be exploding
on on already this is
what i was saying not a
combinatorial approach yeah
with without uh unlimited
uh degree of freedom
this is what i was like that
was my final joke is like
but not a combinatorial
approach you can go in many
different directions and
imagining different options.
I think that pretty
much is for today.
Then, do we want to have
office hour next week?
Traditionally,
with the previous
instructor, sometimes
we do have, sometimes we don't.
I kind of remember you were
mentioning some singing.
i'm okay coming to the
office hour next week but
there will be no singing
okay so nobody wants to
hear me singing i promise
you and i cannot play
anything so i'm really
like musically untalented
it's a it's a family thing
in my family we are all
horrible singers but we
used to sing in the car
just for the sake of
because we were all terrible
so nobody could complain
about the others but
really for sure i don't
want myself recorded singing
all right so just to try
and get me to sing yes yes
i was what i was waiting
for volunteers wheel i
mean i can try to see if
alex want to come and sing
we can invite a special
guest alex had been promising
me for a long time to uh
to play the background
for something and i was
going to say well he was
going to sing part and i
was going to sing part of
it and he never got around
to it so okay let me let
me see if i can arrange it
i don't make any promise
the only promise i make
everybody is that i'm not
gonna sing and you should
be thankful and i'm also
not gonna play i took
piano lessons like a couple
of years ago and i'm not
very good at that either
I understand music
It's just my fingers
Yeah I was never good I was
never good with instruments
My fingers are just not
dexterous enough For piano
and guitar and things like
that But that's more than
anybody needs to know It's
been fun Thanks everyone
So what are we
going to do Sheen
Well
Reading some poem
Victor seems to be, yes,
that's been some fun.
Shall we end the meeting?
Yeah, and anyway, so, well,
students will find
out next time.
All right, thank you all,
and have a good week.
Bye, everyone. Bye.